Guide to the Americans for UNESCO Collection, 1929-2014 MS2361
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Americans for UNESCO
1929-2014
bulk 2003-2014
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Unesco
MS2361
8.5 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Some files are restricted as they contain personal financial records. Archivists will review folders before researchers are allowed to access it, and remove any restricted content.
Arrangement
The collection has been organized into 2 series, the Governance and Association Records series and the Publications series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Americans for UNESCO, October, 2016 (Accession Number 2016-117)
Biographical / Historical
Americans for UNESCO aims at supporting and enhancing US participation with UNESCO, in collaboration with the US National Commission, the Department of State, the UN Association, the UN Foundation, concerned government agencies, research institutes, universities and NGOs, and UNESCO itself. Regarding UNESCO and its programs, AU aims to increase public knowledge in America, foster civil-sector support, promote institutional and individual interaction, facilitate collaborative interaction, and organize interactive meetings where appropriate.
Source: https://2001-2009.state.gov/p/io/unesco/members/48674.htm accessed October 12, 2018
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records and publications created or held by Americans for UNESCO. Researchers interested in the history of the organization or in international relations, especially as it pertains to culture and education, will find these records useful.
Education; International relations and culture; International education; Cultural relations
- Governance and Association Records, 1997-2014; 2003-2014; Series 1; 7.5 Linear Feet
  Conditions Governing Access
  Some materials are restricted. Restricted files have a note attached to them.
  Arrangement
  Material is arranged in the same order it was in when held in the office of Americans for UNESCO
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of papers held in the offices of Americans for UNESCO. The records primarily concern the business of operating
  - P & R III: Fobes, 2005-2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jack Fobes, 2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 17 June 2005 - Speeches, 2005-2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John Edwin Fobes, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fobes - 17 June 2005, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hazel Fobes, 2005-2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Loose in Box], 2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Invitation - 17/6/05, 2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Publications, 2005-2009; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Printing Jobs, 2004-2006; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - List Finances, 2004; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Blog, January, 2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Web Master, 2003-2004; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Website, 2005-2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [Committee & Commission Meetings], 2005-2007; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - UNESCO & U.S.A. Partnerships, 2006-2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Resignations, May, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - World Heritage Youth Forum, March, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO / Bilbao Prize, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO Annual Meeting, May, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO Laura Bush Traveling Fellowship, 2008-2009; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO Annual Meeting, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO slides, May, 2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mailing, 2003-2008; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - U.S. National Committee for UNESCO, 2008; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - U.S. National Commission on UNESCO, 1967, 2003-2008; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - A Brief History of the U.S. National Commission for UNESCO: 1970-1983, January 11, 2011; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations by Social & Human Sciences Committee - U.S. National Commission on UNESCO, September 17, 2010; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - UNESCO Youth & College Programs, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO: World Genesis Foundation, 2010; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO: Meeting December 1st, 2010, December, 2010; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Message from Andre Varchaver to Members of U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, 2009-2010; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO - Annual Conference - Correspondence, 2008-2010; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - UNESCO Accountable Decentralization, November, 2006; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO Members, 2006; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Roundtable Meeting of U.S. National Commission for UNESCO Director-General Bokova, January 19, 2010; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, 2009; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, 2008; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, 2007; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - UNESCO Center for Peace Board Meeting, January 13, 2009; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - UNESCO Center for Peace, 2005-2007; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Center for Peace, 2005-2007; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Model U.N., 2005-2006; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - UNESCO Center for Peace, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO List of Commissioners, April 6, 2011; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - DTA NYC Mission, 2003; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Mission UNESCO Club Leaders Paris, 2003-2004; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Americans for UNESCO Mission Statement, 2003; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - John Brademas, 2001-2005; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Advisory Council, 2004-2009; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Advisory Council, 2004-2011; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Americans for UNESCO List of Directors, October 22, 2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Roger Coate, 2006-2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Rita Colwell, 2005; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rita Colwell - Water Prize, March 22, 2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - John Daly, August 5, 2009; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Mary H. Futrell, 2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bio - Mary H. Futrell, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Annette Hartenstein - Future of Americans for UNESCO, 2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Melinda Kimble, September 15, 2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Irving Lerch, 2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Obituary Papers for James Goodrich McCargar, 1997-2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Patrice Lyons, 2003-2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Richard K. Nobbe, 2003-2011; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Frank Method, 2006; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sid Passman, 2006-2009; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Susan Rauch College Art Association, 2003-2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - InterConnections 21, 2002, 2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Larry Seaquist, 2004-2006; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Seth Spaulding, February 28, 2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Michael Southwick, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Ms. E. Vargas-Baron, 2004-2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Andre Varchaver, 2003; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - United States Mission to UNESCO, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - R. Wanner "A Look Forward" and & Kettering, 2008-2009; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - R. Wanner - UNF Letter to UNESCO, Undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Ray Wanner, 1946, 2005-2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Mr. P. Hemily Trustee Emeriti, October 31, 2003; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Fund from Board, February 20, 2006; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Bios, 2004-2006; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Board Meeting - Friday, 18 November 2011, 2006-2011; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Board Meeting - 15 October 2010, 2007, 2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Board Meeting - 15 October 2010 Voting for Proxy, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Board Meeting - 15 October 2010 Attendance, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Board Meeting - 15 October 2010 Comments on Document Look Forward, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Board Meeting - 15 October 2010 U.S. National Commission for UNESCO Matters, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Board Meeting - 2011, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Board Meeting - 20 May 2010, May 20, 2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Board Meeting - 10 May 2010, 2009-2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Agenda - Board Meeting - 20 May 2010, May 20, 2010; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Board Meeting - 13 January 2009, 2008-2009; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Agenda - Board Meeting - 13 January 2009, January 13, 2009; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Board Meeting - 27 May 2008, May 27, 2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Board Meeting - 27 May 2008, 2004-2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Minutes - Board Meeting -, May 27, 2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Minutes - Board Meeting - 30 April 2007, April 30, 2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Agenda - Board Meeting - 27 May 2008, 2008-2009; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Board Meeting - 31 October 2007, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Minutes - Board Meeting - 31 October 2007, October 31, 2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Board Meeting - 31 October 2007, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Board Meeting - Monday, 30 April 2007, 2006-2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Board Meeting - 26 September 2006, 2006-2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Board Meeting - 23 May 2006, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Board Meeting Special Membership Committee, June 5, 2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Nomination Committee, 2003-2008; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Board, 2003-2007; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Board Meetings, 2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Board Meeting - 30 January 2006, 2005-2006; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Board Meeting - Monday, 24 October 2005, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Board Meeting - IIE 1400 K Street, NW Room 6 A/B - 18 May 2005, 9:30AM to 1:00PM, Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Board Meeting - 18 February 2004, 2003-2004; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Commission on Effective Teachers & Teaching, December 10-11, 2010; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Commission on Effective Teachers and Teaching, February 11-12, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Education Beyond 2015, April 9, 2014; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Position Paper on Education Beyond 2015, Undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "From language to knowledge: how to mobilize our ultimate renewable resource?" Address by Irina Bokova, Director-General of UNESCO on the occasion at the University of Iceland, May 26, 2014; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO: Commission Update, May 30, 2014; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Gender Equality Action Plan 2013-2015, Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - UNESCO Priority Gender Equality Action Plan 2014-2021, Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - International Matters, March 12, 2014; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Commission on Effective Teachers and Teaching, December 10-11, 2010; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - National Education Association Commission, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - National Education Association Commission, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - National Education Association Summit, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - National Education Association Summit - OECD, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - U.N. Foundation, 2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - U.S. National Commission, 2011-2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - UNA-NCA, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - World Affairs Council, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - World Affairs Council/UNESCO, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - 501 (c)(3), 2006, 2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Fundraising Letters, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Telephone - GWU, 2012-2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Check Negotiations, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Checks, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Fundraising Letter List, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Financial Reports, 2012-2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Fundraising Campaign, 2011-2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Governance Committee Report, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Special Membership Committee, June 5, 2007; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Nominating Committee, 2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Small Group Meeting, January 12, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Board Meeting, April 27, 2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Board Meeting, 2011-2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Board Meeting, 2005, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Board Meeting, 2010; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Board Meeting, October 15, 2010; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Board Meeting, 2012-2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Board Meeting, 2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - By-Laws, 2008-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Annual Resolution, 2011-2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Board of Directors, 2011-2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Advisory Council, 2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Mailing List, August 24, 2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Seminar, 2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Executive Committee, 2010-2011; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Vision Statement, Circa 2010; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - UNESCO Chair, 2009-2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Internship, 2012-2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Letter to Congress, 2011-2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Future of Americans for UNESCO, 2011-2012; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Website, Undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Strategic Planning, Undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Gender, Jobs, and Education: Prospects and Realities in the Asia-Pacific, 2013; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Fundraising, 2006-2008; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fundraising, 2005-2006; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fundraising, 2005-2006; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Finances, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising, 2003, 2011; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Fundraising - Call for Contribution, 2003-2007; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Kathleen Waldron, July, 2004; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Award Design-Event, 2004; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Ford Foundation, 2003-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Finance Committee Fundraising, 2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Fundraising, 2009; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - David W. Packard, 2004; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - The Mary Duke Biddle Foundation, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - John D & Catherine T MacArthur Foundation, 2004-2006; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Fundraising, 2009-2010; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Fundraising, 2005-2011; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Circular Letters & Fundraising Letters, 2003-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Clubs UNESCO - WFUCA, 2003-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Constitution of the World Federation of UNESCO Clubs, Centres, and Associations, 2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Clubs UNESCO - WFUCA, 2006-2007; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Club UNESCO Census, 2010; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - WFUCA, 2003-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - WFUCA, September 13, 2010; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - WFUCA, 2003-2007; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - UNESCO Clubs WFUCA, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - 5th World Congress of WFUCA, July 9-13, 1999; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Board Meeting, April 24, 2003; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Board Meeting, June 25, 2003; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Board Meeting, 2003; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Board Meeting, 2003; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Board Meeting, 2004; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Board Meeting, 2004; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Board Meeting, 2004; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Board Meeting, February 18, 2004; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Strategic Planning Meeting, 2004-2005; Series 1 (Box 5, Folder 35)
- Publications, 1929-2014; 1995-2014; Series 2; 1 Linear Feet
  Material is arranged alphabetically by title.
  Series consists of books, pamphlets, and other forms of published reports produced by UNESCO or other international organizations and held by Americans for UNESCO.
  - Balancing Change and Tradition in Global Education Reform [Order Form], 2004; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Democratie Questions et Reponses, 1995; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - The Education for All Teacher Training Package Volume 1, 1995; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - The Education for All Teacher Training Package Volume 2, 1995; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Education Transforms Lives, 2013; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Higher Education in the Twenty-First Century: Vision and Action, October, 1998; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Histoires de Diplomatie Culturelle des Origines a 1995, April, 1995; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Insult Laws: In Contempt of Justice A Guide to Evolution of Insult Laws in 2009, 2010; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Intergovernmental Conference on Cultural Policies for Development: Final Report, 1998; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - King Juan Carlos I of Spain Center of New York University Report on Activities, 2000; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - La Culture a l'epreuve de la mondialisation (Culture Confronts Globalization), 1999; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - League of Nations Handbook of International Organizations, 1929; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - NO to Illicit Traffic in Cultural Property, November, 2000; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - [Pamphlets], Undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Public Thinking About Americans' Role in the World: An Analysis of Results from the 2003-04 National Issues Forum, 2004; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Public Thought and Foreign Policy: Essays on Public Deliberations about Americans' Role in the World, 2005; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Regulatory Framework for the Use of the Name, Emblem, Abbreviation and/or Sponsorship of UNESCO, 2002; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - SHS Publications Catalogue, 2000-2004; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Social and Human Guides to Partnerships, 2004; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Tendances Mondial en Matiere de Liberte d'Expression et Developpement des Medias, 2014; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - United Nations Foundation, September, 2005; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - UNESCO User's Manual 2.04, Undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - UNESCO: What is it? What does it do?, 2007; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - UNESCO Without U.S. Funding? Implications for Education Worldwide, 2012; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - The U.S. and UNESCO: Jobs, Peace, and Security, Undated; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - World Heritage and Sustainable Development: The Role of Local Communities, 2011; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - World Heritage in Young Hands: An Interactive Educational Kit, 2010; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - World Heritage Information Kit, March, 2005; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - World Press Freedom Day 2011, May 1-3, 2011; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - World Heritage in the United States of America: The U.S. Tentative List, 2008; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - World Heritage List, May 14, 1998; Series 1 (Box 6, Folder 31)